帝王影业出品
iCelery军团倾情奉献
本字幕根据知识共享-署名-相同方式共享-4.0国际（CC-BY-SA4.0)协议发布
http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.zh
WHO博士与戴立克
《物理学中的方法、性质和哲学》出版于1960年，本书是一本供非物理学专业的大学师生和具有高中以上文化水平的读者的参考读物
《科学学》是一本总结新领域科研成果的科普书
《老鹰漫画》最初于 1950 年至 1969 年发行，并于 1982 年至 1994 年重印，其每周销量近 100 万册
真有趣
Most exciting. Hm.
天哪  Ian一会就要来了 我得去做点准备
Goodness, Ian will be here in a moment. I must go and get ready.
那是谁
Oh? Who's that?
爷爷 我和你提过他很多次了
Grandfather! I told you about him dozens of times.
-她的新男朋友  -原来如此
- Her new boyfriend. - Ooh!
我想见见他 他叫什么名字
Yes, I look fonnard to meeting him. What's his name?
Ian
Ian.
天哪 肯定是他来了
Goodness, that'll be him now!
Susie 做个乖孩子 去开下门 好吗
Susie, be a dear and answer the door, will you?
好吧
All right.
-很高兴你来拜访  -是的 又是你开的门
- Glad you dropped in. - Ok, so you caught me again.
爷爷 这位是Ian Chesterton
Grandfather, this is Ian Chesterton.
-我很高兴终于见到你了  -你好
- I am so very glad to meet you at last. - Oh, hi.
-抱歉  -你真是太好了
- Oh, excuse me. - How extremely kind of you.
很周到 谢谢
Most thoughtful. Thank you.
这是给Barbara的软夹心巧克力 这是她的最爱
They're for Barbara. They're soft centres. Her favourite kind.
是的 当然是给她的 她刚刚还在这
Oh, yes, of course, yes. Well, she was here a moment ago.
别介意 不如坐下来等她
Well, er, never mind. Why don't you sit down while you're waiting for her?
哦
Oh...
你坐到了软夹心巧克力
Soft centres.
别介意
Well, never mind.
这些软夹心巧克力还有的是
Plenty more where that came from.
-别坐 打住  -怎么了
- No! Wait! - What is it?
这是超电离电动预振荡器
A super-ionised electro-kinetic pre-oscillator.
你差点坐上去了
And you nearly sat on it.
这是我多年的研究成果 也是新发明的一部分
Years of research work. Part of my new invention.
你想来看看吗 走吧走吧 我带你看看
Would you like to see it? Come on. Come on, I'll show you.
他理解不了的
He wouldn't understand.
任何人只要下决心就能理解科学的 你能理解的
Anyone can understand science if they only put their minds to it. You can.
这可不一样
Well, that's different.
-我们得给给Harold一个机会  -Ian
- Oh, well, let's give Harold a chance. - Ian.
-你说什么  -我叫Ian WHO博士
- I beg your pardon? - Yes, my name's Ian, dr who.
哦 你好
Oh! How do you do?
好了 来吧 快来
Yes, yes, well, come along, then. Come along.
谢谢 Susie 我们走吧
Thank you, susie. Off we go.
你先请 走吧
After you, erm... yes, right.
这个就是我最新的发明
There. My latest invention.
-一个警察亭吗  -当然不是
- What, a police box? - Of course not!
-这是TARDIS  -TARDIS是什么
- This is tardis. - Tardis?
它代表时间和空间的相对维度
It stands for time and relative dimension in space.
进去吧 进去
- Oh. - Go inside. Go on.
是吗
Yeah?
但是它里面比外面大 怎么做到的
But it's so big in here and yet it's so small from outside. How come?
在电动力学理论中 空间通过扩张 来容纳
In electro-kinetic theory, space expands to accommodate the time necessary
-包含其维度所需的时间  -我的科学小助手
- to encompass its dimensions. - My little fellow scientist.
我们已经在TARDIS上花了很多年的时间
We've been working on tardis for many years.
这是最后一个组件
This is the final component.
年轻人 你有幸成为我们时空机器的
You are privileged, young man, to be the first visitor
第一位来访者
to our time and space machine.
在这 我能设置前往
There. I can now set the controls
我们想去的时空中的任意地方
for anywhere in time and space that we wish to go.
一旦我拉下操纵杆 这个房间和里面的东西
When I push that lever, this room and everything in it
会分解成各自的电荷组分
will dissolve into their respective component electrical charges.
也就是我们的组成部分
We're all made up of them.
这些电荷会被传送到时空中
These charges will then be transferred in time and space
然后按照正确的顺序 在恰当的地方复原
and reassembled in their proper order and their proper place.
呃 我觉得我应该 呃
Er, well, I think I ought to be, er...
哦 我就知道你们都在这
Oh, I thought you'd all be in here.
-你好 亲爱的  -你好
- Hello, darling. - Hello.
小伙子 你知道自己刚刚做了什么吗
Young man, do you know what you have just done?
你把我们传送到了时空中 而我还没做任何设置
You have transferred us in time and space and I hadn't even set the controls.
我不知道我们在哪了
Now I don't know where we are.
我们可能在宇宙中的任何时间 任何地点
We could be anywhere in the universe and at any time!
相当令人兴奋 不是吗
Rather exciting, isn't it?
听着 我不知道你在这个房间里搞了什么戏法
Look, I don't know how you do the magic with the inside of this room,
但你要说我们在宇宙中的某个地方......
but as far as being somewhere else in the universe...
让我们来看看我们到哪了
Let's see where we are.
-爷爷 我们在哪  -Susan  亲爱的 别走太远
- Grandfather, where are we? - Susan, dear, don't go too far yet.
这里肯定发生过森林火灾
There must have been a forest fire.
温度高得难以形容
The heat must have been indescribable.
把地球燃成了灰烬
It's turned the earth into ashes.
哦 起码土壤没那么糟糕 这还长有灌木和树
Oh, well, the soil can't be that bad. It still grows these shrubs and trees.
看那个
Look at that.
一座石化的丛林
A petrified jungle!
多有趣啊 太有趣了
How interesting. This is most interesting.
如果这对你来说都一样 先生
Well, if it's all the same to you, sir,
也许我们现在可以回家了 对吗
perhaps we could be making our way home now, huh?
什么 要错过了解这个未知星球的机会吗
What, and miss the chance of learning something about an unknown planet?
胆小鬼 换我就会去做个调查
Coward. I for one am going to investigate.
走吧 爷爷
Come on, grandfather.
-走吧 爷爷  -我来了 亲爱的
- Come on, grandfather! - I'm coming, darling.
-真迷人  -爷爷 看这个
- Fascinating. - Grandfather, look at this!
这是什么呢
And what is it then?
哎呀 这看起来就像 郁金香
Byjingo! That looks like a... looks like a tulip.
这是费城百合
It's a lilium philadelphicum.
是吗
Is it now?
那是朵费城百合 是吗
It's a lilium philadelphicum, is it? Hm.
Ian
Ian!
Ian 你还好吗
Oh, Ian! Are you all right?
-没受伤吧 小伙子  -没
- Nothing broken, lad? - No.
又一个软夹心巧克力罢了
It was another soft centre.
那在这坐一会 就坐这
Well, come and sit over... look, over here.
坐好了
There we are.
我们永远都不会知道那是什么 对吧 Susie
We shall never know what that was, will we, susie?
爷爷 看
Grandfather, look!
-这次你发现了什么  -看
- What have you found this time? - Look!
天哪 是一座城市
Upon my soul! A city!
真叫人意外
But how extraordinary!
一座大城市
A huge city!
你看到人了吗
Can you see any people?
没 一个人都没有
No. No one at all.
没生命 没移动的迹象
No life, no movement.
这边
Here.
-你看到人了吗  -没
- Can you see anyone? - No.
-让我们去调查一下  -是的 调查一下
- Let's investigate. - Oh, yes, let's!
这里发生过很可怕的事
Something terrible happened here.
这里很危险
This place is dangerous.
我能感觉到
I can feel it.
-我觉得我们该离开了  -你不必来说服我
- I wish we could leave. - Well, you don't have to convince me.
呃 WHO博士
Er, dr who.
我觉得我们应该离开这个地方
I think we should get out of this place.
但是听着 Susan刚发现了一座城市
But look, Susan's just found a city.
你不想先探索一下吗
Wouldn't you like to explore it first?
我的家人们在等我回家
Erm, well, they're expecting me at home.
他们会想我在哪 我 我觉得我们应该回去了
They'll be wondering where I am. I... I think we should go back.
好吧
Oh, well.
嘿 嘿 嘿 是我 是我 是我
Hey, hey, hey! It's me, it's me, it's me!
你确定吗 Susan 亲爱的
Are you sure, Susan, dear?
这个星球上不可能会有任何人类存在
It's not possible for any human form to exist on this planet.
那是一双手 还碰了我
It was a hand! It touched me!
嗯 我想知道那是谁 或者说那是什么
Hm. Then I'd like to find out who or what it was.
我可不想知道
Rather you than me.
我们不知道自己在哪 在哪个时间点
We don't know where we are, what period in time.
我们不知道外面可能是什么
We don't know what might be out there.
用扫描仪看看
The scanner.
没人 没东西
Nobody. Not a thing.
肯定有东西制造了那个噪音
Well, something must have made that noise
而我不想搞明白那是什么
and I don't want to find out what it is.
-你不能设置好回家的路径吗  -当然能
- Can't you set the controls for home? - Certainly.
-都设置好了  -你把我们带来了
- All set. - Well, you got us here.
你最好能让我们回去
You might as well get us back.
怎么了
What's the matter?
有地方出问题了
There's something wrong somewhere.
我用故障探测器试试
I'll try the fault locator.
K7 是流体连接器部件
K7. The fluid link section.
是的 流体连接器
That's it. The fluid link.
它的末端被撞击错位了
This end has been jarred out of position.
一些流体都流完了
Some of the fluid has run out.
-你有备用的吗  -我们不需要
- Have you got a spare? - Oh, we don't need one.
只需要重新加注水银就行了 我在Tory那放了一点 糟了
This just needs refilling with Mercury. I have some in my iabora... Tory.
万一这个星球上没有水银的话
Supposing there isn't any Mercury on this planet.
我们得去城市里试试 这是我们唯一可能找到一点的地方
We'll have to try the city. It's about the only place we're likely to find any.
小心
Be careful!
- Susan! - Susan!
-Susan  -Susan
好的 谢谢 Susie
Right. Thank you, susie.
看上去是某种药物 我好奇这是什么
It looks like some sort of drug. I wonder what it is.
所以刚刚有人在这
So there was someone here.
我们回家后 我要对这些药物做些测试 是的
I shall make some tests on these when we get home. Yes.
现在 帮我把这些东西放进去好吗 Susan 亲爱的 谢谢
Now, perhaps you'll put those inside for me, will you, Susan, dear? Thank you.
那么现在
And now...
向城市进发
For the city.
这是个陡坡 不是吗 Susie
That was a steep climb, wasn't it, susie?
-你还好吗  -我没事 亲爱的
- What's the matter? - It's all right, dear.
爷爷 你还好吗
Grandfather, are you all right?
有点累 我的腿脚不利索了
Just a little tired. My legs are rather weak.
我自我感觉不太好
I don't feel too well myself.
这海拔一定很高
Must be the altitude.
做个深呼吸 小伙子
Take a good, deep breath, lad.
好多了 是的
That's better. Yes.
像这样的城市里 一定有实验室
Now, in a city like this, there must be laboratories.
我们能在那找到一些水银
Now, that's where we could find some Mercury.
我建议大家分头行动 然后在这里会合
Now, I suggest we all take different directions and then all meet back here.
怎么样 可以吗 好的
How's that? Yes? Right.
那么你跟我走 Susie
Now, you come along with me, susie.
你去那扇门
You take that one.
遇到麻烦了吗 小伙子
Having trouble, lad?
我没法穿过这扇门
I can't get through those doors!
让我们试试另一条路
Let's try the other way.
Susan 亲爱的 在我们试着让门开着的时候 你先坐在这
Susan, dear, you sit on there while we try to keep those doors open.
当我大喊的时候 你有多快跑多快 好女孩
When I shout, you run just as fast as you can. Good girl.
准备好了吗 好了 Susan 跑 快点
Ready? Now, Susan! Run! Fast!
别走太快了 小伙子 别走太快了
Not too fast, lad. Not too fast.
走吧 年轻人
Come on, lad.
-等等  -怎么了
- Wait. - What is it?
听
Listen.
声音从那边传过来的
It's coming from over there.
卧槽
Well!
Susan Susan 亲爱的
Susan! Susan, dear.
是测量仪 我好奇是用来测量什么的
Measuring instruments. But to measure what, I wonder?
这是某种盖格计数器
This is some sort of geiger counter.
已经过了危险数值
And it is past the danger point.
大气已经被高浓度放射性坠尘污染了
The atmosphere is polluted with a very high level of fallout.
我们必须找到Barbara 然后回到TARDIS里
Then we must find Barbara and get back to tardis.
即便如此 在我们找到水银前也无法离开
Even if we do, we can't leave until we get some Mercury.
小伙子 我必须承认
Young man, I have to confess,
其实流体连接器没出问题
there is nothing wrong with the fluid link.
我只是不想没探索这座城市就离开
I just didn't want to leave until we had explored the city.
-请原谅我  -让我们离开这里
- Please forgive me. - Well, let's get out of here.
你们走在我们前面
You will move ahead of us
并且遵循指示
and follow directions.
这边
This way.
他很快就会恢复
He will recover shortly.
搜他身
Search him.
这对你们毫无价值 它...
That is of no value to you! It...
往这边走
Come this way.
-谢天谢地 你们来了  -很高兴你没事
- Thank goodness you've come! - I'm so glad you're safe!
Ian Ian 你怎么了
Ian! Ian, what happened to you?
-哦 没事  -他一会就没事了
- Oh, it's nothing. - He'll be all right in a minute.
-是的  -Ian
- Yeah. - Ian!
别担心 别担心 Barbara 只是暂时的休克
Don't worry. Don't worry, Barbara. It is only a temporary shock.
把他扶起来 用力
Get him up over here. Up.
至少我们会合了 你感觉如何
At least we're all together. How do you feel?
有点虚弱和头晕
Sort of weak and giddy.
-Susan呢  -我也是
- And Susan? - I feel the same.
我们在楼上发现了一个盖革计数器 这颗星球的辐射水平很高
We found a geiger counter upstairs. This planet has a high level of radiation,
也许是失落的原子战争导致的
perhaps the result of some lost atomic war.
我们一直都在公共场合 暴露其中
All the time we were in the open, we were exposed to it.
在我们身上会发生什么 爷爷
What's gonna happen to us, grandfather?
除非我们能得到治疗 不然毫无生还的希望
Unless we can get some treatment, we have little hope of survival.
我们的囚犯有辐射病的迹象
Our prisoners are showing signs of radiation sickness.
但他们还没有因此死亡
But they have not yet perished from it.
他们一定找到了能让自身免疫的东西
They must have found something that makes them immune
而我们必须留在这些保护机器里
while we must remain in these protective machines
而且不能离开我们的城市
and cannot go out of our city.
如果我们能免疫 就能离开这座城市了
If we had it, we could leave the city,
然后消灭其他人 独占这座城市
destroy all others and have the planet for ourselves.
让我们偷听一下囚犯们的话
Let us overhear what our prisoners say.
或许他们会给我们答案
Perhaps they will give us the answer.
如果某种生命形式存在于这座城市外
'If some form of life does exist outside this city,
他们一定已经发现了一种抗辐射的药
'they must have discovered an anti-radiation drug.'
怎么说
'well?'
我们在TARDIS外面找到的那盒玻璃瓶 记得吗
'that box of glass vials we found outside tardis. Remember?'
你们四个中的一个
one of you four
必须走出这座城市
must go outside the city.
-谁去  -为什么要去
- Which will it be? - Why?
几个世纪前
Many centuries ago,
这颗星球上有两个种族
there were two peoples on this planet.
我们戴立克和Thal人
Ourselves, the daleks, and the thals.
中子战争后
After the neutronic war,
我们的祖先退隐到这座城市中
our forefathers retired into the city,
靠这个外壳保护自己
protected by this clothing.
绝大部分Thal人死于这场战争
Most of the thals perished in the war.
那些幸存并留在这颗星球上的人
Those who survived and remain on this planet
都是可怕的变异怪物
are horrible mutations, monsters.
他们有一种治疗辐射病的药物
They have a drug which cures the sickness of radiation.
如果我们得到这种药
If we get the drug,
我们会分你们一些
we will give some to you.
没有那个东西 你们会死的
Without it, you will die.
我们的状态都不好
None of us is well enough to go.
你们必须去一个
One of you must.
我去
I'll go.
-Susan  -这太危险了
- Susan! - It's too dangerous.
快点
Hurry.
这个小孩在靠近森林
The young one is approaching the forest.
她一会就会到
She will be there in a moment now.
如果她把药带回来了
If she returns with the drug,
我要允许囚犯们使用一些吗
am I to allow the prisoners to use some?
不 他们唯一的价值
No. Their only value
就是把药带给我们
is to bring us the drug
让我们能复制
to duplicate for ourselves.
让他们去死
Let them die.
哦 天哪
Oh, dear.
我很抱歉
I'm so sorry.
都是我的错
It was all my fault.
哦 天哪  他变得更糟了 他什么意思 怎么就是他的错了
Oh, dear, he's getting worse. What does he mean, it's all his fault?
流体连接器没出任何问题
There was nothing wrong with the fluid link.
而现在戴立克把那玩意从他身上拿走了
And now the daleks have taken it from him.
我们该怎么做
What are we going to do?
什么都做不了 只能等
Nothing we can do. Just wait.
希望Susan平安无事
Hope nothing happens to Susan.
谁在那
Who's there?
你是谁 你想干嘛
Who are you? What do you want?
我叫Alydon 我是Thal人
My name is alydon. I am a Thal.
我刚刚在森林里试着和你说话
I tried to speak to you in the forest just now.
抱歉吓到了你
I'm sorry I frightened you.
我回来是确保你知道怎么用我留给你们的药
I came back to make sure you knew how to use the drugs I left you.
但是我在这没看到人
But I found no one here.
其他人成了城市里戴立克的囚犯
The others are prisoners of the daleks in the city.
-有人在城市里吗  -他们让我回来拿药
- There are people in the city? - They sent me back for the drugs.
是他们自己想要 还是给你的朋友们的
Do they want them for themselves or for your friends?
我不知道 我不相信他们
I don't know. I don't trust them.
我再给你一些
I shall give you a second supply
你必须藏得严严实实的
which you must hide as best you can.
谢谢 但是我不理解
Thank you. But I don't understand.
他们说你们变异了
They said you were mutations.
终局之战后有不少人变异了
There were many mutations after the final war.
大部分都死了
Most of them perished.
但是两只手 两只眼的样貌 是最适合生存的
But this form, two hands, two eyes, has always been best for survival.
但是他们称你们为怪物
But they called you monsters.
如果他们叫我们怪物 他们长什么样
If they call us monsters, what must they be like?
-你从船上带来了什么吗  -没
- Have you brought anything else from your ship? - No.
你在藏东西
You are hiding something.
给我看看
Show it to me.
把这些药给你的朋友
Give these other drugs to your friends.
-你的份 Babara 亲爱的  -谢谢
- Here's yours, Barbara, dear. - Thank you.
那么 一个Thal人给了你这件斗篷吗 Suan
So, a Thal gave you this cape, Susan?
是的 他叫Alydon 他告诉我他们住得离着很远
Yes. His name's alydon. He told me his people live far from here
但是今年他们的庄稼被毁了 他们来这里找食物
but this year their crops were ruined and they came here in search of food.
他说他的族人很乐意为戴立克提供这种药物的配方
'He said his people would gladly give the daleks the formula for the drug
只要戴立克提供他们食物作为回报
'if the daleks would give them food in return.'
我们不需要他们的配方
we do not need their formula.
现在 这个女孩已经把药给我们了
Now that the girl has brought us the drug,
我们能自己制备出来
we can make it ourselves.
我们将从这些保护机器中
We will rid ourselves
解脱自己
of these protective machines,
摆脱城市的限制
move beyond the limits of the city
然后消灭Thal人
and destroy the thals.
现在 有更好的办法
No, there is a better way.
我们给他们提供食物
Let us offer them food,
把他们带到我们城市里
bring them into the city.
-设圈套吗  -是的
- A trap? - Yes.
他们不会怀疑吗
Will they not suspect anything?
如果这个信息是由他们的朋友 那个女孩写的
Not if the message is written by their friend,
他们就不会怀疑
the young girl.
Ian
Ian!
我给你们带了一些食物和水
I have brought you more food and water.
-这个女孩和我走  -去干嘛
- The small one is to come with me. - What for?
你们已经有药了 什么时候放我们走
You have the drug. When are you going to set us free?
别动
Stay!
我们要去帮Thal人
We are going to help the thals,
这是你们想我们去做的
which is what you want us to do.
他们怎么知道我们想去帮Thal人
How do they know we wanted to help the thals?
加上这句
Add this:
戴立克
"The daleks
只是想帮你们
"want only to help you
并且与你们交友
"and to be friends."
现在签上你的名字
Now sign your name!
我找到了
'I've found it.
就在这
'Up there.
他们是靠这个知道我们在做什么的
'That's how they know what we're doing.'
我们想要的就是这个信息
all we wanted was this message.
当Thal人来拿食物的时候
When the thals come to collect the food,
我们会消灭他们
we will destroy them.
你们俩究竟在干嘛
What on earth are you two doing?
让我们能在不被监视的情况下交流
We'll be able to talk without them seeing or hearing us.
-能拿下来吗  -是的
- Is it coming away? - Yes.
好的 用力拽 我会抓紧你 啊
Right, pull hard. I'll hold you. Agh!
我们的囚犯很聪明
Our prisoners are intelligent.
而且可能很危险
And perhaps dangerous.
为什么不消灭他们
Why not exterminate them?
他们曾对我们有用
They have been useful to us once.
说不定还会有用
They may be again.
首先 让我们消灭Thal人
First, let us exterminate the thals.
我们应该更换镜片吗
Shall we replace the lens?
不必
No need.
我们已经从囚犯身上学到很多了
We have learned enough from our prisoners.
而且他们被关在不会造成威胁的地方
And we have them where they can do no harm.
他们把Thal人带进陷阱中
They're bringing the thals into a trap.
我们能做什么吗
Isn't there anything we can do?
如果我们能找到戴立克的弱点 只要一个
If we could find a weakness in the daleks, just one...
他们被保护着 能轻易地移动
They are protected, they can move easily
并且有能使人瘫痪或是被消灭的武器
and they have weapons which can paralyse or destroy.
-我们无能为力  -那Thal人将被毁灭
- There is nothing we can do. - Then the thals are doomed.
要是戴立克拒绝帮助我们
Suppose the daleks refuse to help us.
那我们就不得不回自己的地方了
Then we shall have to start back for our own country.
-穿过沙漠吗 我们会死很多人  -但是如果戴立克有食物
- Across the desert? Many of us will die. - But if the daleks have food,
-他们怎么会拒绝我们呢  -看
- how can they refuse it to us? - Look.
我在城门找到了这个
I found this at the gates of the city.
是那个小女孩写的
It is from the young girl.
她说戴立克希望与我们交友
She says that the dalek people wish to make friends with us.
他们在大厅给我们留了食物
Food will be left for us in their great hall.
我们明天就去取
We are to collect it tomorrow!
慢着 你怎么知道能信任戴立克呢
Stop! How do you know you can trust the daleks?
他们的祖先对我们发动了一场大战
Their ancestors waged a great war against us,
毁灭了我们的星球 造成了如此大的破坏
destroyed our planet, caused all this devastation.
但那是陈年往事了 现在他们希望与我们交友 并提供我们食物
But that was long ago! Now they wish to make friends with us, offer us food.
没理由不相信他们的善意
There's no reason not to believe their good intentions.
我们早上就去戴立克的城市
We will go to the city of the daleks in the morning.
门 墙 地板
The doors, the walls, the floor
都是金属材质的
are all made of metal.
也许这就是戴立克的弱点
Perhaps this is the daleks' weakness.
什么意思
What do you mean?
他们移动的时候 有一股熟悉的臭味
Whenever they move, there is a familiar odour.
是的 我也注意到了 我在想是在哪闻到的呢...
Yes, I've noticed that too. I was trying to remember where...
在游乐场 你能在碰碰车上闻到同样的味道
A fairground. You get the same smell from the dodgem cars.
是由电火花导致的臭氧
It's ozone, made by electric sparks.
电能 但不是我们熟知的那种电
Electric power. Not the sort of electricity we know,
是某种静电
but some form of static electricity.
他们身上的盔甲
Those armour suits they wear
实际上是通过地板的金属获取能量的机器
are actually machines that pick up their power through the metal of the floor.
现在 如果我们能让这些机器与电源绝缘
Now, if we could insulate those machines from their power source,
-他们会孤立无援  -是的
- they would be hopeless. - Yes.
但是我们能用什么当绝缘体呢
But what can we use as an insulator?
-用我的斗篷  -Susan
- My cape! - Susan!
它由某种塑料材料制成
It's made of some sort of plastic material.
应该足够厚了
It should be thick enough.
是的 这会很简单 不是吗
Sure. It's gonna be easy, isn't it?
打扰一下 戴立克先生 你介意移动到这件斗篷上吗
"Excuse me, mr dalek, would you care to move onto this cape?"
离门远点
Move back from the door!
你们拿上食物
You, take the food.
他们总是呆在外面的走廊里
They always stay outside in the corridor.
你没法在不被发现的情况下接近他们
You can't get near them without being seen.
我们就不能砸碎他们眼睛上的镜片吗 或者把Susan的斗篷扔在上面
Couldn't we smash that lens in their eye? Or throw Susan's cape over it?
那你用什么来绝缘呢
Then what do you use to insulate him from the floor?
我想我找到东西了
I think I've got it!
如果他准时 那他随时都会在 准备好了吗 小伙子
If he's on time, he'll be here any second. All ready, lad?
离门远一点 Susan 亲爱的
Just a little farther away from the door, Susan, dear.
太近会引起他怀疑
Too close will make him suspicious.
准备好了吗 Babara
All ready, Barbara?
他来了
He's coming.
接着
Take this.
这够你们今天的份了
It must last you till tomorrow.
发生什么了
What is happening?
为什么门关不上
Why do not the doors close?
-戴立克  -怎么了 啊
- Dalek! - Yes? Agh!
救我 救命 救我
Help me! Help! Help me!
-救我 救命  -给 用这个试试
- Help me! Help! - Here! Try this!
救我 救命 囚犯试图逃跑
Help me! Help! Prisoners trying to escape!
救我 我看不见他们 我看不见他们
Help me! Cannot see them! Cannot see them!
救命 我看不见他们
Help! Cannot see them!
-救命 救我 快点  -推过来
- Help! Help me! Quickly! - Round here!
-我控制住他了  -不能让他们跑了
- I've got him! - They must not get away!
救我 救我
Help me! Help me!
起作用了 大家干得漂亮
It worked. Well done, everybody.
你觉得他死了吗
Do you think he's dead?
现在 你和Babara去看守走廊
Now, you and Barbara go and keep watch on the corridor.
走吧 小伙子 把他移到那边去
Come along, lad. Move it over to there.
小心 他可能还是很危险
Careful! It could still be dangerous!
把斗篷捡起来 这个机器要怎么打开
Pick up the cape. How does this thing open?
你能应付吗 把他放在那边
Can you manage it? Put it over there.
-现在怎么办  -现在你进去
- Now what? - Now you get inside.
-干嘛  -假装你是戴立克
- What for? - Pretend you're a dalek.
如果我们遇到任何人 你就说带我们去审问
If we meet anyone, you're taking us to be questioned.
-但是如果被发现了怎么办  -我们无路可退
- Yeah, but what if they find out? - We'll be no worse off than we are now.
好了 进去吧 小伙子 时间宝贵
Come along, get inside, lad! Speed is essential!
装载进舱
Hatch coming down.
-我什么都看不见  -什么
- I can't see anything. - What?
-我什么都看不见  -眼睛没清理
- I can't see anything. - The eye.
嘿 这里到处都是开关 我应该摸索一下吗
Hey, this thing's full of controls in here. Should I try a few?
哦 求你了 别试 什么都别碰 我们会推你走
Oh, for heaven's sake, no, don't touch a thing! We'll move you.
准备好了吗 Babara 好的 走吧
Ready, Barbara? Right, on with it.
Susan 带我我们走那条你回TARDIS时 戴立克带你走的路
Susan, show us the way the daleks took you when you went back to tardis.
好的 在走廊尽头左转
All right. Turn left at the end of the corridor.
我就走的这条路 有一扇被戴立克看守的大门
This is the way I came. There's a big door with a dalek on guard.
门后就是电梯
Beyond the door is the lift.
看你的了 小伙子 要勇敢
Now it's up to you, lad. Courage.
-嗷  -哦 抱歉
- Ow. - Ooh, sorry.
停下
Stop.
囚犯已被传讯
The prisoners have been called for questioning.
我没被通知 稍等
I have not been informed. Wait.
我不会去的 我不去
I won't go! I won't!
阻止她 阻止她
Halt her! Halt her!
帮我把他们带进去
Help me get them inside.
需要我帮你把他们带到四楼吗
Shall I help you take them to the fourth level?
不必 关门
No. Close the doors.
你真机智 Susie
That was clever of you, susie!
我刚把囚犯送到七号竖井
I have just passed the prisoners into shaft seven.
等待指示
'Stand by.'
能把我弄出来吗 这里面很热
Can you get me out of this thing? It's hot in here.
好
Yep.
没有囚犯们的行动令
'There is no movement order for the prisoners.
抓住他们
'Hold them.'
-快把我弄出来  -我们在这么干了 小伙子
- Hurry up and get me out of here! - We're trying, lad!
门锁上了
The door is locked.
他们一定是把开关熔了 紧急警报
They must have fused it. Emergency alarm!
怎么了
What was that?
-是警报 他们知道我们已经逃跑了  -试着从里面往上推
- An alarm be!!! They know we've escaped! - Try to push it up from the inside!
-你以为我在干嘛  -好吧 再用点力 小伙子
- What do you think I've been doing? - Well, try harder, lad!
他们正在破门而入
They're cutting through the door!
电梯就离地板不远
The lift has stopped just short of the floor.
我们不能让他进来 试试推他进去
We'll never get him in. Let's try.
别管我了 如果我们都被抓了就毫无意义了
Leave me! No sense in us all being captured.
-不行  -别管我了
- No! - Leave me!
-不行  -1 2 3
- No! - One, two, three...
Ian
Ian!
戴立克还要花多久能破门
How long will it take to cut through that door?
-很快  -但是即使他出来了
- Not very long. - But even if he does get out,
他也被困在这里了 而这是唯一的逃跑方式
he's stuck down there! This is the only way of escape!
-爷爷 我们不能抛弃他  -我们能怎么做
- Grandfather, we can't just leave him! - What can we do?
看
Look!
阻止他 阻止他
Stop it! Stop it!
把电梯弄下来
Bring it down!
-哦 Ian  -你是怎么做到的
- Oh, Ian! - How did you manage it?
我们得找条出路
We must find a way out.
Thal人来拿食物补给了
The thals are coming for their food supplies.
他们在直奔埋伏
They're walking straight into an ambush.
我们的命令不是抓住他们
Our orders are not to capture them.
要彻底消灭他们
They are to be completely destroyed.
他们不许逃跑 他们必须死
They must not escape. They must die.
我明白
I understand.
快点
Hurry up!
嘿 帮我搭把手
Hey! Give me a hand!
现在 1 2 3
Now, one, two, three!
我们必须警告Thal人
We must warn the thals!
快来帮忙
Help!
搞定
Got it!
这是个陷阱 回去 快跑
It's a trap! Go back! Run!
谢谢你警告我们
Thank you for warning us.
对不起……我们没能及时救下你的朋友
I'm sorry... we were not in time to save your friend.
但是我不明白为什么
But I don't understand why.
为什么他们想杀我们 我们带着和平而来
Why did they want to kill us? We came in peace.
你们和他们不同
You are different from them,
他们害怕任何不一样的东西
and they are afraid of anything different.
他们一旦感到害怕 就将其消灭
And what people are afraid of, they try to destroy.
如果我们能跟他们讲道理
If we could reason with them...
他们不讲道理 他们只想征服
They are beyond reason. They wish only to conquer.
-那我们能做什么呢  -什么 当然是与他们战斗
- What can we do, then? - Why, fight them!
我们热爱和平 我们没理由杀害他人
We're a peaceful people. We see no reason to kill others.
但是即使你们知道他们想杀你们吗
But even when you know that they would kill you?
终局之战几乎摧毁了这颗星球上一切
The last war destroyed almost everything on this planet,
只留下了......像这样的东西
left it... like this.
-我们不想再打仗了  -可以理解
- We do not want another. - That is understandable.
我希望有办法能帮你们
I wish there was some way we could help you.
你们必须离开
You must go.
我们会幸存的
We shall survive.
再见
Goodbye.
祝你们好运
And good luck.
女士
Madam.
再见
Yes.
走吧 孩子
Come along, children.
-再见  -再见
- Goodbye. - Goodbye.
Thal人的药被复制了
The drug of the thals has been duplicated.
好样的 我们会在生产部门做测试
Good. We will test it on this work section.
如果有效
If it is effective,
我们将卸下这些机器
we will discard these machines
然后出去消灭Thal人
and go out and destroy the thals.
-检查无误  -检查无误 Babara呢
- Check. - Check. Barbara?
检查无误
Check.
-检查无误  -检查无误
- Check. - Check.
是流体连接器
The fluid link!
哦 不 我们该怎么做
Oh, no. What are we going to do?
-我们必须把它拿回来  -怎么拿
- We must get it back. - How?
只有Thal人能帮我们
Only the thals can help us.
我们很乐意帮你们 你们救了我们很多人
We'd like to help you. You saved many of our people.
但是我们不希望杀死其他人
But we do not wish to kill others.
而且我也不想我的族人被杀害
And I do not want any of my people to be killed.
要是戴立克从城市里出来攻击你们呢
Supposing the daleks come out of their city and attack you?
他们能找到离开城市的办法
They could find a way of getting out of the city.
他们有武器 而你们手无寸铁
They have weapons, you have none.
我们不会战斗
We will not fight.
失去控制
'Out of control.
救我 救我
'Help me. Help me.
失去控制
'Out of control.'
这是试药的那个部门
this is the section to whom we gave the drug.
显然我们戴立克不能用Thal人的药物
It is obvious that we daleks cannot use the drug of the thals.
我们没法离开这些机器
We will not be able to leave these machines
或是走出这座城市
or go out of the city.
那我们就在不离开城市的情况下消灭Thal人
Then we will destroy the thals without leaving the city.
我们会引爆另一颗中子弹
We will explode another neutron bomb
增加整个星球的辐射值
and increase radiation throughout the planet
到时候即使Thal人有药
to a point where even the drug of the thals
也保护不了他们
will not be able to protect them from it.
-我们什么时候引爆炸弹  -立刻
- When shall we explode the bomb? - Immediately.
这些文字包含了我们星球和我的族人完整的历史
These writings contain a complete history of our planet and our people.
真迷人 太迷人了
Fascinating. Absolutely fascinating.
但这些文字可以追溯到近50万年前
But these writings go back nearly half a million years.
这里曾经有一个伟大的文明
There was a great civilisation here once.
毁于战争
Destroyed by the war.
但是你能重建它 孩子 这是值得为之奋斗的
But you can rebuild it, man. Now, surely that is something worth fighting for.
你为什么留着这些文字呢
Why do you keep these writings?
它们是我们族人的历史
They're the history of our people.
除非你们准备好为这一代人的生存而战
A history that will end with this generation
否则这段历史将以这一代人而终结
unless you are prepared to fight for its survival.
你们的一个人已经在城市里被杀了
One of your people was killed in the city.
还有很多人被杀了 而且还会有人被杀 除非你们采取行动
Many others could have been killed and will be unless you take action.
我们不会战斗
We will not fight.
小伙子
Lad.
年轻人
Young man.
你知道为什么戴立克把我们当囚犯吗
Do you know why the daleks held us as prisoners?
他们想在我们身上做实验
They wanted to experiment on us.
也许我们给他们一个你的族人
Perhaps if we gave them one of your people instead,
他们或许会把从我这拿走的一个设备还给我
they might return the piece of equipment they took from me.
-把她带到戴立克那去  -你不能......
- Take her to the daleks. - You can't...
你不能这么做
You cannot do this!
-我还以为你们是我们的朋友  -看到了吗 你会为了什么而战的
- I thought you were our friends! - You see? You will fight for something.
中子弹准备在一个小时内引爆
The neutron bomb will be ready for explosion in one hour.
好样的
Good.
一个小时后
In one hour,
我们将是这颗星球唯一的主人
we will be sole masters of this planet.
这座城市三面环绕着岩墙
The city is surrounded on three sides by rock walls.
第四面被山
The fourth side is protected
和致命的沼泽保护着
by mountains and a deadly swamp.
致命的
Deadly?
有一天我们五个族人去寻找食物
Five of us went looking for food there one day.
只有我的兄弟和我回来了
Only my brother and I came back.
-其他人怎么了  -我们找到了他们 他们还能剩下什么呢
- What happened to the others? - We found them. What was left of them.
沼泽中满是变异体 是这座城市的完美防御
The swamp is alive with mutations. It's a perfect defence for the city.
如果我们能穿过沼泽 我们就能打戴立克一个出其不意
If we could get through that way, we could take the daleks by surprise.
这对我们来说都太危险了
It'll be too dangerous for all of us.
但是我们会派我们勇敢的朋友带头冲锋
But we'll send a small party that way, led by our brave friend.
其余人和我们一起试着找条路靠近城市
The rest will come with us to try to find a way to approach the city.
你去和他一起穿过沼泽
You will go with him through the swamp.
好吧
All right.
你有什么要报告的
What have you to report?
我们的长程探测器监测到Thal人移动
Our long-range scanners detect movement by the thals.
一大波人在靠近城墙
A large party is approaching the city walls.
实施七号防御计划
Bring defence plan seven into operation.
警告全体部门
Alert all sections.
另一部分人在前往城市后方
Another group is moving towards the rear of the city.
他们无法通过那里 他们会死
They cannot pass. They will die.
-我们永远不可能过去的  -我们必须试试
- We'll never get through! - We must try.
-这里满是变异体  -你一直在吓自己
- It's full of mutations! - You keep your fears to yourself!
我不想你让别人失望
I don't want you upsetting the others.
好了 走吧
Right, come on!
哦 我们就不能休息一会吗
Oh, can't we rest just a minute?
行 休息一会
All right, rest.
哦 我去洗把脸
Oh, I could do with a wash.
嘿 嘿
Hey! Hey!
-我在水里看到了大家伙  -那是什么
- I saw a great big thing in the water! - What was it?
我不知道 我等不及要搞清楚
I don't know. I didn't wait to find out.
-你还好吗  -看
- Are you all right? - Look!
戴立克肯定是从这里取水的
The daleks must get their water from here.
这些管子肯定径直穿过山
The pipes must go straight through the mountain,
也许直达戴立克的城市
perhaps into the city of the daleks.
如果我们能找到那条路
If we could find that way...
我来把水壶装满 我们会需要的 我一会追上你们
I'll fill the water bags. We'll need them. I'll catch you up.
好的 走吧
Right, come on!
-哦  -救命 拉我出去
- Oh! - Help! Get me out!
拉我出去
Get me out!
和她呆在一起
Stay with her.
你跟我走
You, come with me.
Elyon怎么了 他在哪
What's happened to elyon? Where is he?
让我们离开这
Let's get out of here.
走吧
Come on!
戴立克用电子仪器把整座城市包围起来了
The daleks have the entire city surrounded with electronic instruments.
现在 我们必须在不被发现的情况下 穿过城墙
Now, to get past the walls of the city, we must find a way of approaching them
-接近他们  -但是你是科学家
- without being detected. - But you're a man of science.
你肯定能想到办法
Surely you can think of a way.
是的 是的 但是没那么简单 年轻人
Yes, yes, but it's not all that easy, young man.
很幸运管子没连入地下
Well, we're lucky they don't go underground.
我们可以跟着它们翻过这座山
We can follow them straight over the mountain.
-怎么翻山  -靠攀爬
- How are we going to do that? - We'll climb.
攀爬吗
Climb?
我只是在担心Babara
I was only thinking about Barbara.
加油
Come on!
这是最后的战役
This is the final battle.
当我们引爆中子弹
When we explode the neutron bomb,
这颗星球会有
there will be more radiation
更强的辐射
on this planet
即使Thal人有药物
than even the thals with their drug
也无法幸存
can survive.
消灭Thal人
Destroy the thals!
今晚我们将完成这场
Tonight we will complete the war
几世纪前就该由我们祖先
which our ancestors should have won
完成的战争
many centuries ago.
消灭Thal人
Destroy the thals!
你觉得我们快到了吗
Do you think we're almost there yet?
我不知道 我们只能跟着这些管子走
I don't know. All we can do is follow the pipes.
我们一定已经度过了最糟的时候 对吧
We must be over the worst of it by now, huh?
好了 走吧
Right, come on.
Ganatus
Ganatus.
怎么了
Yes?
-我想回去  -我们必须去城市里
- I want to go back. - We must get to the city!
他们在这有扫描仪 我要回去
They could have scanners here. I'm going back.
-不 不许回去  -我们会被杀的 我们战胜不了戴立克
- No, you're not! - We'll be killed! We won't defeat the dalkes!
你一直在干嘛
What have you been doing?
现在已经不能回头了
Now there can be no question of going back!
爷爷 我告诉过你要看着蛋糕
Grandfather! I told you to watch the cakes!
-你把它们烤焦了  -哦 是的 蛋糕 糟糕
- Now you've burnt them! - Oh, yes, the cakes. The cakes!
女士
Madam!
请原谅我 我可以借用一下吗
Pardon me, please. May I borrow that just for a moment?
十分感谢
Thank you so much.
年轻人 你还有这些镜子吗
Young man, do you have any more of these mirrors?
-怎么了 我有  -请拿过来
- Why, yes. - Get them, please.
-拿得越多越好  -拿来干嘛
- Collect as many as you can. - Why?
它们也许是让我们去到城市里的方法
They may be our way of getting into the city.
拿着
Here.
-你要干嘛  -跳过去
- What are you going to do? - Jump it.
我们把这个当安全绳
We'll use this as a safety line.
我先走
I'll go first.
轮到你了
Now you.
我觉得我需要更长的助跑
I think I need a longer run.
别担心 很简单的
Don't worry, it's easy.
抓住
Catch!
我要过来了
Coming over.
你必须跳过来 这是唯一的办法
You must jump. It's the only way.
抓住绳子
Now catch it!
别担心 这很安全 听着 我会抓住你
Don't worry, it's perfectly safe. Look, I'll catch you.
哦 不
Oh, no!
短波光辐射
Short-wave light radiations.
这应该会干扰他们的探测器
That should confuse their detectors.
他们在攻击我们的仪器
They are attacking our instruments.
蠢货 我们能打他们个措手不及
Fools! We can take them by surprise.
呆在那别动
Stay where you are.
不许动
Do not move.
不许动 不许动
Do not move. Do not move.
你们是我们的囚犯
You are our prisoners.
不 Antodus 不
No, antodus! No!
嘿 把我弄出去
Hey! Get me out of here!
-他没事  -哦 真叫人宽慰
- He's all right! - Oh, what a relief!
但是为什么你们必须消灭Thal人
But why must you destroy the thals?
你们为什么不能和平共处并且共享知识呢
Why can't you live together in peace and share your knowledge?
我们将成为这里的统治者
We will be the rulers here.
我们什么都不会分享
We will share nothing.
我们将引爆中子弹
We will explode the neutronic bomb.
开始倒计时
Begin the countdown.
不
No.
博士和他的孙女被戴立克抓走当囚犯了
The doctor and his granddaughter have been taken prisoner by the daleks.
-现在就靠我们了  -我们能做些什么
- Now it is up to us! - What can we do?
我们能战斗
We can fight!
Thal人再一次向城市移动
the thals are moving towards the city once more.
但是现在没关系了
But it does not matter now.
不久后 他们都会死
In a few minutes, they will all be dead.
等等 我有事情要告诉你们
Wait! I have something to tell you.
你们不知道我们是怎么来这颗星球的
You do not know how we came to this planet.
我有一台能穿过时空屏障的机器
I have a machine which is capable of crossing the barriers of time and space.
如果你们不引爆炸弹 我就告诉你们它的秘密
I will tell you its secrets if you do not explode the bomb.
我们不相信你能造出这样的机器
We do not believe you are capable of creating such a machine.
-是真的  -你从我这拿走了很重要的一个组件
- It's true! - You took a vital part of it from me.
检查它 你会发现它一定属于某台复杂的机器
Examine it. You will see that it must belong to some complicated machine.
-那个部件在我这  -52
- I have it here. - '52.'
那个机器在哪
where is the machine?
在城外的石化森林里
In the petrified forest outside the city.
很好 我们会去检查
Good. We will examine it
然后用它征服其他的星球
and use it to conquer other planets.
但是没有我 你们操作不了
But you could not operate it without me.
我们会想到办法的
We will find a way.
我们要怎么进去
How do we get in?
Thal人在城市里 Thal人进来了 情况紧急
Thals in city. Thals here. Emergency.
呆在那别动
Stay where you are.
你们被困住了
You are trapped.
呆在那别动
Stay where you are.
你们逃不掉的
You cannot get away.
呆在那别动
Stay where you are!
下来 立即下来
Come down! Come down at once!
囚犯正在逃跑
Prisoners escaping.
向上级指挥报告
Reporting to upper level control.
四名Thal人在向控制室楼层移动
'Four thals are moving to control room level.
拦截他们
'Intercept them.'
注意
attention.
四名Thal人在向控制室楼层移动
Four thals moving to upper control room level.
-27  -消灭他们
- '27.' - destroy them.
呆在那别动
Stay where you are.
你们逃不掉的
You cannot get away.
你们被困住了
You are trapped.
-Alydon  -城墙上没有戴立克
- Alydon! - There were no daleks at the walls.
-我们轻易就进到了城市里  -肯定有原因的
- We came into the city easily. - Then there must be a reason.
Ian 不
Ian, no!
走吧
Come on!
Babara 注意身后
Barbara! Look behind you!
小伙子
Lad!
停止倒计时 炸弹会摧毁这颗星球
Stop the countdown! The bomb will destroy the planet!
戴立克看这
Daleks!
-Susie 你没事吧  -发生什么了
- Susie, are you all right? - What happened?
-Babara  -他们都死了
- Barbara. - They're all dead.
是的
Yes.
那是我的幸运数字
That's my lucky number.
已经设好回家的路径 让我们和我们的朋友们告别
All set for home. Let's say goodbye to our friends.
走吧
Come along.
真是隆重的接待
Quite a reception.
你从戴立克的统治中拯救了我的族人
You saved our people from the rule of the daleks.
我们没什么能用来感谢的
We do not have much with which to thank you,
但是我们希望你们拿上这个来记住我们
but we would like you to take these to remember us.
-你们真好  -谢谢
- How very kind of you. - Thank you.
很感谢 我们会珍惜它们
Thank you so much. We will treasure them.
谢谢
Thank you.
-再见  -再见
- Goodbye. - Goodbye.
-拜  -再见
- Bye. - Goodbye.
-再见  -再见
- Goodbye. - Goodbye.
- Goodbye! - Goodbye.
-再见  -再见
- Goodbye. - Goodbye.
- Goodbye! - Goodbye.
你在伦敦这么穿会显得很滑稽
You'll look pretty funny wearing that in London.
谢谢 Babara
Thank you, Barbara.
哦 现在我们要回到自己的时间和地点了
Oh! And now we will return to our own time and place.
-谢天谢地  -只需要推动操纵杆 小伙子
- Thank goodness for that. - Just push the lever, lad.
啊 现在如果你打开门
Ah. Now if you'll open the door,
你会发现我们回到了自家的小花园里
you will find we're back in our own little garden.
回家总是很愉快的 不是吗
Always nice to get home, isn't it?
嘿 你应该来看看......
Hey! You ought to see what...
小心 他们过来了
Look out! They're coming!
做点什么啊
Well, do something!